<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The trepan: being a true relation, full of stupendious variety, of the strange practises of Mehetabel the wife of Edward Jones, and Elizabeth wife of Lieutenant John Pigeon, sister to the said Mehetabel. Wherein is discovered the subtil method whereby they cheated Mr. Wessel Goodwin, a dyar in Southwark, and all his children of a fair estate: with sundry copies of letters, perfumed locks of hair, and verses they sent him, and many other notable devices belonging to the art of trepanning.</title>
            <author>Vernon, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V253B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E884_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207304</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866363</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866363</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118634</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95861)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118634)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E884[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The trepan: being a true relation, full of stupendious variety, of the strange practises of Mehetabel the wife of Edward Jones, and Elizabeth wife of Lieutenant John Pigeon, sister to the said Mehetabel. Wherein is discovered the subtil method whereby they cheated Mr. Wessel Goodwin, a dyar in Southwark, and all his children of a fair estate: with sundry copies of letters, perfumed locks of hair, and verses they sent him, and many other notable devices belonging to the art of trepanning.</title>
                  <author>Vernon, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Samuel Vernon by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 20".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jones, Mehetabell.</term>
               <term>Pigeon, Elizabeth.</term>
               <term>Goodwin, Wessel.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fraud --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Rogues and vagabonds --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118634:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TREPAN: BEING A true RELATION, full of ſtupendious variety, of the ſtrange practiſes of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hetabel</hi> the Wife of <hi>Edward Jones,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Wife of Lieutenant <hi>John Pigeon,</hi> Siſter to the ſaid <hi>Mehetabel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is Diſcovered The ſubtil Method whereby they Cheated Mr. <hi>Weſſel Goodwin,</hi> a Dyar in Southwark, and all his Children of a fair Eſtate: With ſundry Copies of Letters, perfumed Locks of Hair, and Verſes they ſent him, and many other notable devices Belonging to The ART of <hi>TREPANNING.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov 6.26.</hi>
               </bibl> For by means of a Whoriſh Woman, a man is brought to a piece of bread, and the Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſs will hunt for the precious life.</q>
            <p>Printed in the year, 1656.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:118634:2"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> being a man profeſsing Religion, they put on a great ſeeming ſhew of Holineſs, whereby they with fained words ſtole into the very heart of this poor old man, and then made merchandize of him, &amp; finding his wife a judicious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet woman, not to be gained neither with the lute nor the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick of their deceitful tongues, they ſecretly inſinuate to Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> that his wife did not ſhew that duty &amp; reſpect as ſhe ought, but aimed to govern her Husband, though all the neighborhood will juſtifie her to have been a moſt vertuous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, &amp; a faithful, loving, reſpectful wife; how far they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with this device to make diviſion between them, is well known to ſome, but ſeeing they are both dead, I forbear any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but Doct. <hi>Mayerne</hi> her Phyſician told me, that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe ſhe died of was Grief; ſhe died, <hi>ann. 1647.</hi> and very op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunely for their purpoſe. A little before her death, with the help of ſome friends, ſhe prevailed upon him to take his eldeſt ſon <hi>Andrew</hi> into Partnerſhip with him, who having newly married a vertuous young maid of good Parentage, might be a ſtay and comfort to the old man after her deceaſe. Well, <hi>Mrs. Goodwin</hi> is dead, &amp; <hi>Mr. Goodwin</hi> now more then ever frequents <hi>Pauls-alley</hi> in <hi>Red croſs-ſtreet,</hi> the place of theſe two ſiſters abode, now they begin to act ſtrongly, and cloſe firſt with him in this manner, they tell him <hi>Mr. Jones</hi> is a wicked man, and in the ſight of God no husband, having forfeited his intereſt, &amp; ſhe free to marry whom ſhe pleaſe, &amp; having muffled this ſhallow old mans conſcience by many ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til inſinuating devices, draw him firſt into a league of love with her, then for the fairer carrying on of the buſineſs, <hi>Mr. Hanſard Knowles</hi> is imployed to draw a Bill of Divorce
<pb facs="tcp:118634:2"/> between Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> and his wife, although he had lived <hi>18.</hi> years in lawful wedlock with her, and ſhe have by him <hi>5</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: then by many practiſes they endeavor one while to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> to be gone beyond Sea, Mrs. <hi>Pigeon</hi> offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him a ſum of money if he would ſo do; but that failing, they arreſt him in fained actions &amp; caſt him in Priſon, &amp; by thoſe practiſes ſo afflicted him, that at laſt he yielded to quit the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſo went into <hi>Norfolk,</hi> where to this day he abideth.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Goodwin</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> thus removed, the game playes fair, now Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> is there day &amp; night, nothing but dalliance &amp; entertainments, carrying them into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſpending his own &amp; his ſon &amp; partners eſtate upon them, now they poſſeſs him at pleaſure, cauſe him at two ſeveral times to make his Will, wherein he gave to Mrs. <hi>Jones 600.</hi> l. that ſo they might have that for a Pledge in caſe he died before the Deſign were perfect; one of which Wills at the requeſt of Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> by the direction of <hi>Mrs. Pigeon,</hi> was drawn at the <hi>Mewſe</hi> by Lieut. <hi>Pigeon,</hi> husband to the ſaid <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> though much againſt his mind, but to buy his peace with his imperious wife: &amp; the other by Mr. <hi>H. Coleborn,</hi> Scrivener, at his houſe in <hi>Budge Rowe.</hi> And here having mentioned <hi>Mr. Pigeon,</hi> I muſt give you a brief accompt what life he leads with this projecting woman, who being thus active for her ſiſter, you may imagine is not idle for her ſelf; ſhe was formerly the widow of one Mr. <hi>Starkey</hi> an Apothecary at <hi>London-ſtone,</hi> whoſe death (as ſhe hath ſince confeſſed to <hi>Mr. Pigeon</hi>) ſhe procured; ſoon after ſhe married Lieut. <hi>Pigeon,</hi> then an Officer in the Army, a man of good parts and a fair eſtate; ſhortly after their marriage ſhe woes him to
<pb facs="tcp:118634:3"/> make her a promiſe upon Oath, in caſe he died, to give her all his eſtate; which he for good reaſons refuſing, ſhe peremptorily refuſeth him her Bed, and yet at the ſame time uſes all the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous practiſes ſhe could imagine, plyes him with high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocative meats &amp; drinks to inflame; &amp; then after all, will you ſwear to give me all? if you will not, if you touch me I will cry murder; by theſe &amp; many other practiſes, not fit to be mentioned, at the laſt ſhe obtained her end, and prevailed with him to make over all his eſtate to <hi>Hen. Coleborn</hi> &amp; ſome other pe ſons in truſt for her: and wheras by this he thought he had won her for ever, ſhe now is more inſolent then before; now ſhe makes him a drudge in all her Projects, and if he ſtick at any thing, then two Beds, and then if you touch me I will cry murder, and now conſults with her Confeſſor Mr. <hi>Knowles</hi> how ſhe may be Divorced from him, till at laſt <hi>Mr. Pigeon</hi> over-come with their practiſes, gave ſome words to <hi>Mr. Knowles</hi> which occaſioned a fray, in which <hi>Mr. Knowles,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Pigeon,</hi> and ſome rude perſons that <hi>Knowles</hi> called in were ſoundly beaten; but this beating they ſo improved, that at a Court-martial they procured <hi>Mr. Pigeon</hi> to be Caſhier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Army and Impriſoned; and to make all yet ſurer, ſhe with ſome perſons fit for her purpoſe makes Oath before the Lords Commiſsioners of the Great Seal, That ſhe went in danger of her life, and ſo obtained a Writ of <hi>Special Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicavit,</hi> which ſhe kept dormant by her to awe him from coming near or diſturbing of her, and ſo <hi>Mr. Pigeon</hi> quit of impriſonment, with-draws alſo into the Countrey: Now they carry all before them, all things favour them, now they ply <hi>Mr. Goodwin</hi> to take heed of his Children; now they
<pb facs="tcp:118634:3"/> draw all <hi>Mr. Goodwins</hi> ſervants into their confederacy, excepting on <hi>Roger Crey</hi> that deteſted their practiſes, he falls ſuddenly ſick, they Phyſick him, and boaſting of their Skill, charge his maſter to uſe no other Phyſician, and that he counterfeited, till the Diſeaſe grew ſo high, that <hi>Andrew Goodwin</hi> privately carried his Water to Doctor <hi>Burnet,</hi> who ſaid he was a dead man, and that he died for want of means in time, &amp; accordingly that night he died in their hands.</p>
            <p>Another obſtacle was young <hi>Mrs. Goodwin,</hi> who hath often, before good witneſs, affirmed, That her heart was broke with their wicked practiſes, in making diſſention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Father and Son, and the apprehenſion of the Ruine ſhe ſaw coming upon the Family; but the Grand Rub in the Project was <hi>Andrew Goodwin,</hi> whom they ſought all ways imaginable to caſt out of Partnerſhip, by daily exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Father againſt him, by breaking open his Counting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe and Trunks in his abſence, <hi>Mrs. Pigeon</hi> ſending for the Smith, and cauſing him in the old mans name to do it, and taking thence all his Papers and Accompts, then cauſing <hi>Mr. Goodwin</hi> to imploy one <hi>Mr. Lewis</hi> an able Accomptant, to make up the Accompts between Father and Son in order to his caſting out and their getting in, to whom as the ſaid <hi>Mr. Lewis</hi> affirmed before the Commiſsioners, ſhe offered <hi>30.</hi> l. as a Bribe, if he would ſo draw up the Accompt as that <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> might have nothing in the Stock, and ſo be caſt out as a Bankrupt: And the better to colour their coming in, which they were now ready for, they draw into their ſnare <hi>James Goodwin</hi> the youngeſt ſon, a ſilly ſchool-boy, who was then fitting to be put to prentice; this Boy they having firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled,
<pb facs="tcp:118634:4"/> draw into a marriage with Mrs. <hi>Jones</hi> her eldeſt daughter, as meer a Child as he, and preſently they are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and ſo theſe two ſuccesful projecting ſiſters with their Children and Servants come all to inhabite at the Dye-houſe, where now they beſtir them: they firſt warn <hi>Andrew,</hi> the Partner, to depart the houſe within <hi>14.</hi> dayes, Mrs. <hi>Pigeon</hi> telling him, She never undertook any Deſign but ſhe brought it to perfection: the <hi>14.</hi> dayes expired, being in <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 1653.</hi> about mid-night, they ſend out their engine, <hi>James Goodwin,</hi> for two Sergeants, and two Bayliffs they had hired, having before entred an Action of <hi>1000.</hi> l. againſt the ſaid <hi>Andrew</hi> for pretended breach of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, theſe Officers are brought in as theeves over the ditch, <hi>Andrew</hi> having the Keyes of the Gate in his Chamber where he was faſt aſleep in bed, Mrs. <hi>Pigeon</hi> brings them up, furniſhes them with an Iron Crow; and the Door pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving difficult to be forced, ſhe cryes, <hi>Mr. Goodwin,</hi> Let them break down the Wall, it is your own Houſe; ſo they ſeized and carried him away to Priſon, and then by aſsigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and bills of ſale from old <hi>Mr. Goodwin,</hi> and ſuch like devices, with <hi>Mr. Hen. Coleborn's</hi> help, ſhe got poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and title to <hi>Mr. Goodwins</hi> and his Sons whole Eſtate; what followed you will finde in the enſuing Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Report drawn up by the Worſhipful Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, by Order of His Highneſs the Lord Protector, to which I refer you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg.</hi> 3. <hi>line</hi> 20. <hi>for</hi> do, intereſt <hi>read</hi> ſo intereſt: <hi>pag.</hi> 7. <hi>line</hi> 33. <hi>dele</hi> all: <hi>line</hi> 35. <hi>for</hi> ſharp <hi>read</hi> ſtrange: <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. <hi>line</hi> 28. <hi>for</hi> into his Grave, <hi>read</hi> into diſgrace.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118634:4"/>
            <head>THE TREPAN.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the precedent Relation of Miſtris <hi>Jones</hi> and Miſtris <hi>Pigeons</hi> practiſes, you have ſeen them by many ſubtile and wicked ſteps, become poſſeſſors of all old Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> and his Sons Eſtate: While old Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> was alive, they wrought at a diſtance, drawing from the old man, now and then, ſums of ten, twenty, thirty pounds at a time, as upon Oath hath been witneſſed; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides much good Proviſion he ſupplied them withal, both for back and belly. But ſhe, now dead, this would not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie them, they ſaw they had an admirable ſubject, and that encouraged them to a higher deſign: An old man, that though he had a weak head, yet an obſtinate will; a man, though inexorable to the faithful counſel of true friends, eſpecially if it thwarted his appetite, yet more facil than a Child to yield to the ſeductions of glavering Flatterers; for which trade theſe two Siſters are moſt exquiſitely qualified: and to all this they had the advantage of many years ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, had ſtudied his Temper, and could work him to their pleaſure.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118634:5"/>
            <p>In brief, by many deceitful ſtratagems, which the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary old man perceived not, they wrought him, as you have heard, to make a ſinful adultrous Contract of Marriage with Miſtris <hi>Jones,</hi> to give her by Will a great part of his Eſtate, to a moſt unnatural hatred of all his dutiful Children, to betray his Son <hi>James,</hi> a child, into marriage with <hi>Lydia Jones,</hi> a mear child alſo, that ſo they might have entrance into the houſe to caſt out his Son and Partner <hi>Andrew</hi> in a moſt inhumane manner; and in fine, by Judgments, Bills of Sale, Aſſignments, and ſuch practiſes, to make over all his own, and his Sons Eſtate, to Mr. <hi>Henry Coleborn</hi> for the uſe of <hi>Elizabeth Pigeon;</hi> who thereupon takes Poſſeſſion of the Houſe, Stock, and Trade, utterly excluding <hi>Andrew</hi> and the reſt of the Children from an Eſtate of 2000. l. which Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> by aſſiſtance of a provident Wife, had been almoſt 40. years labouring for.</p>
            <p>Thus far the former Relation gives you account; now I proceed to a Diſcovery of what they have ſince acted, wherein (beſides my promiſe not to prevaricate from the truth) the Reader ſhall have ſuch unqueſtionable proofs as will ſilence all Cavils; and ſtranger things than theſe you hear not often.</p>
            <p>But firſt I muſt here give you an account of Mr. <hi>Edward Jones:</hi> In the former Relation you have ſeen how after five years abſence from <hi>London,</hi> being conſtrained in his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he comes to <hi>London;</hi> and going to <hi>Pauls</hi>-Alley to ſee his Children, was, by theſe two ſiſters procurement, in five ſeveral Actions, in all to the value of about 1000. l. arreſted and caſt into priſon, though of all this he owed not one pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and of divers of thoſe men, whoſe names they had uſed, had never ſeen their faces: There he continued many months, and had he not been ſupplied by his Tenants in St. <hi>Johns ſtreet,</hi> muſt there have periſhed.</p>
            <p>During his impriſonment, they often ſend his Children to him, who are inſtructed to ask him enſnaring queſtions, that ſo they may feel how he reſents his Condition: and when they fonnd him (as they thought) indifferently morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, then they endeavour to draw him to their wicked
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118634:5"/> Conditions: the chief of which were, Firſt, That he make over all his Eſtate to his Wife by Truſtees; and, Secondly, and chiefly, That he immediately depart the City with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to return no more, that ſo ſhe might be free for old Mr. <hi>Goodwin:</hi> The firſt part he enclined to upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; but the ſecond he utterly rejected, and ſo the Treaty broke off. And now Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> ſomewhat en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the honeſty of ſome of his Tenants, who ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied him with the Arrears of the Rent due five years in their hands, ever-ſince his departure; all which Miſtris <hi>Jones</hi> might have received Quarterly upon Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> his Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances which he ſent her from <hi>Norwich,</hi> but ſhe utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, becauſe by thoſe Receipts ſhe muſt acknowledge Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> to be her Husband: and Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> purſe being then full, ſhe let the Rents (as aforeſaid) reſt in their hands, which proved happily for Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> in this Condition. And now obſerving Mr. <hi>E. C.</hi> the Counſellour to be very active with theſe two ſiſters; and judging that it muſt be upon ſome Conſideration that a perſon of Mr. <hi>C</hi> 's rank ſhould do, intereſt himſelf in his Wives Cauſe, he procured a truſty Friend to go to Mr. <hi>C</hi> his houſe at <hi>Marybone,</hi> who there ſaw ſeveral parcels of Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> his Goods in a Parlour, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ancient Pictures of value; but not being admitted into any other Room, he cannot tell what there was more, but theſe he knoweth to have been Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> his Goods. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> exhibited a Bill in Chancery agaiſt Miſtris <hi>Pigeon,</hi> Mr. <hi>C.</hi> and ſeveral others for the examination of the Counterfeit Actions he was Arreſted for, and the Diſcovery of his Goods; and by this means got a Releaſe of thoſe Counterfeit Actions, and was quitted and immediately went again into the Country: During this unjuſt impriſonment, he ſpent almoſt 80. l. which he affirmed he intended to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide every penny amongſt his Children. And ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that Trepan, with loſſe and diſgrace to the two Siſters.</p>
            <p>And here having made this degreſſion, I ſhall alſo inſert the Trepaning of one <hi>Eſay Aſpinwal</hi> by Miſtris <hi>Pigeon:</hi> He was ſome years ſince Apprentice to one Mr. <hi>Hardy</hi> a Salter
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118634:6"/> neer <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> and now living in <hi>Lambeth.</hi> Near to this youth there lived a Maid-ſervant, one <hi>Mary Northcote,</hi> aged about 36 yeares; this wench leaving her Service, was after entertained by Miſtris <hi>Pigeon:</hi> where after a while Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> over-hearing her in the night to Sigh and Groan much, ſhe tells her Husband ſhe muſt know what this meant; Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> checking her pragmatick nature, ſtill prying into the ſecrets of others, diſwaded her all he could, but ſhe vowed ſhe would know: and to be ſhort, the next day got this Wench into her Inquiſition, and never left ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in her Conſcience till ſhe diſcovered to her, There had been ſome love between the ſaid young man and ſhe; and further confeſſed, That he had layen with her above forty times, and had promiſed her marriage. Whereupon Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> ſends for the young man; Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> ſtill diſwading her from medling in this matter, and adviſing her rather to turn her away: but ſhe replyes, You are a fool; Now will I have out of this Wench what Service I pleaſe: the young man came, ſhe Catechiſes him into a Confeſſion, cauſes him to write and ſubſcribe it, and ſo diſmiſſes him; who having after ſome few years finiſhed his apprentiſhip, and ſet up a little Shop for himſelf; which Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of, ſends for the young man, and having before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand all her inſtruments in readineſs, demands of him if he will now marry her Maid? The young man replyes, That he was new ſet up, his Stock ſmall, and did not yet ſee how he ſhould ſubſiſt with a Wife, and therefore deſires ſome reſpite: But Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> not rhus ſatisfied, gives the Trepan-watch-word, and preſently two Sergeants appear, who hale him away to a Tavern in <hi>Wood-ſtreet</hi> to capitulate, where Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> follows; the poor young man by this time had ſent for his Brother, a Country-man in Town, who hearing the Caſe, and ſeeing into what hands his Brother was fallen, over-come with grief before he could utter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſwelled ſo, that the very buttons burſt from his doublet, and at laſt fell into a moſt bitter lamentation; and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting to Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> his Brothers youth, his Fathers affection to this Son, who ſo ſoon as he ſhould hear of this,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118634:6"/> (being an antient godly Gentleman in the Country) would die with grief, and therefore beg'd, that rather than ingage him in this unequal ſcandalous match, he might make her ſome reaſonable ſatisfaction with Money; (which was the word Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> watcht for) ſhe demanded 500. l. for a Dowry to this old crackt Vaſtal, for whom a clean Whip had been a fitter recompence for ſeducing a poor youth to ſuch wickedneſs: But the Brother urging his Fathers po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and the unreaſonableneſſe of ſuch a Sum; in ſhort, to reſcue his Fathers grey hairs from the grave, and Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> being informed that their Father had given him and his Brother 50. l. a peice, ſhe urged, that if they would give her all, he ſhould go quit; which at laſt they yielded to, and Bonds were ſealed, and after a ſhort time the Money paid to Miſtris <hi>Pigeon,</hi> to the utter undoing of both theſe young men; the ſaid <hi>Eſay</hi> not able by this means to keep open his Shop, went away, and could never ſince be heard of: Fifty pounds of this Money was beſtowed in marriage with this flawed piece to a Shooe-maker, one Mr. <hi>Cheval,</hi> next to <hi>Algate</hi> under <hi>London</hi>-Wall: and for the other 50. l. whether Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> have ſince given to this huſwife, or (as is moſt probable) reſerved in her own hands for Brocage, is uncertain: and ſo alſo concluded that <hi>Trepan.</hi> And now I return to the main ſtory.</p>
            <p>Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> now in poſſeſſion of all Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> and his Sons Eſtate, caſts about how ſhe may improve it, and make it a ſtanding thievery; ſhe firſt plods to all the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and with her diſſembling pretences, alleging all is ſtill done for the good of old Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> prevailed with ſome to continue their Work to the houſe, and ſome new Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers are acquired, as Mr. <hi>John Gold</hi> of <hi>Clapham</hi> their very great friend. And becauſe ſome ſcrupled the ſafety of their Goods, ſhe procures Mr. <hi>Coleborn</hi> to give his ſecurity, as he, in whoſe Name ſhe bought and ſold, retained and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged all, and <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> now at hand, that being the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual time of Payments, ſhe haſtens and importunes them to pay into Mr. <hi>Coleborn</hi> the laſt years Money, about 1200. l. and earned in the Partner-ſhip, who gives them Diſcharges;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118634:7"/> and encouraged with the viſible gains ſhe ſaw in that Trade, ſhe plyes it on all hands, while Miſtris <hi>Jones</hi> (a heavier piece) acts her part with old Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> to keep him in a good humour: now that he and his Children are ſtript of all; but active Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> is every where at the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants for Work, at the Salters for Wares, prying and watching that the Servants ſhall get no vayls, except honeſt Mr. <hi>Anthony Rawlin</hi> that for former good ſervices muſt be a little connived at.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, that <hi>Andrew</hi> may not diſturbe her, one while ſhe threatnes to bring him to Tryal of the 1000. l. Action ſhe had formerly cauſed him to be Arreſted in: Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while commends his good nature, but ſeduced by his wicked Brother <hi>Vernon:</hi> and now having ſettled all, ſhe thinks ſhe may a little retire her ſelf, partly to attend o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Projects, and partly to abate the clamour of people that ſpeak of her and her Siſter <hi>Jones,</hi> as thoſe that had Cheated Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> and all his Children of all. Miſtris <hi>Jones</hi> then is left <hi>in depoſito,</hi> yet Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> between whiles comes in her Hackney Coach to take accompts, and ſee how all is managed: and thus ſhe runs through 1654. and part of 1655. boaſting of her great Gain. But now the Trade began to ſink a pace, and they as faſt in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, nor could they with all their art keep on the paint which daily peeled off from their bold deluding faces: which Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> obſerving, and well knowing that the Dyers Trade, if not ſupplied with Work, is rather fit to bring her behind hand, than to advance her; ſhe therefore in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner quite with-draws both her purſe and preſence, leaving <hi>Mehetabel</hi> to help up the old man; but ſhe that by this time ſaw through her ſiſters Craft, who had uſed her only as a bait to Catch old Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> while Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> caught the Eſtate, and had now ſecured it under Mr. <hi>Colebourns</hi> Name to her own uſe, and being now unwilling to abide all the reproach, while her ſiſter had all the gain, ſhe alſo with draws to the old Den in <hi>Pauls-Alley,</hi> where her ſiſters leads her a ſad life.</p>
            <p>But in what a caſe now is old Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> bereaved of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118634:7"/> Eſtate, Trade, Credit, and which he values more than all, of the Company of his two precious friends; now muſt he to his old march again to <hi>Red-Croſſe-ſtreet,</hi> where he often comes, but finds not his former entertainment: when the two ſiſters uſed to come and meet him at the Garden-door with How do you, dear Sir, precious Mr. <hi>Goodwin?</hi> Very well, I thank you: Indeed Sir you are not well: Indeed I am very well: Indeed, Sir, you are not, the Lord knows you are not well, you look as if you were not well: Indeed I am very well: Are you indeed? Then the Lord be praiſed: and this with ſuch accent and geſture, as made the poor old mans bowels and brains melt within him; and then out came the Capon, and the ſtuffs, and then nothing but meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment mixed with, Dear Sir, have a ſpecial care of your Son <hi>Andrew</hi> that he do not undo you; and be ſure you take no Counſel of your Children, for that were to be ruled by your Cradle: Thus would they draw this poor inconſiderate old man into their ſnare under pretence of Love and care of his Perſon: but the Fiſh once caught, off goes the bait. Now that all is in their hands, and that he comes to them ſtript, with his empty pockets hanging out, now nothing but quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling and cavilling queſtions about the Trade, railing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he goes not amongſt the Cuſtomers for Work, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling at every word he ſaith; and when he ſhews her how they are neceſſitated for Money and Wares, ſhe having drawn all dry, and that he and the Servants are fain to take up Wares and Proviſions upon their own Credit, then like one of King <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Tax-maſters that would have them make Bricks or Money without ſtraw; ſhe tells him plainly ſhe will pay none of his Debts, and bids him work for his living.</p>
            <p>About this time Mr. <hi>Henry Coleborn,</hi> Miſtris <hi>Pigeons</hi> great Friend that had ſheltered all her wicked Projects, falls very ſick of a ſharp Diſeaſe, the Phyſitians doubt him, and ſend him to <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> there he grows worſe and worſe, and perceiving himſelf not like to live, he comes back for <hi>London;</hi> Diligent Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> meets him upon the Road about the mid-way, and by her feined care of his welfare, never leaves
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118634:8"/> till ſhe have perſwaded him into her Coach, and ſo bring him to take up his Lodging at the Rat-trap in <hi>Pauls-alley:</hi> The pretence of his coming there was, that he might be out of the noiſe of buſineſſe: but the deſign that ſhe might perfect ſome Projects that ſhe had in her head, whereof one was to have made a Match between his only Son and her Daughter; but that failing, her next great buſineſſe is, that he aſſign over all the truſt both of Mr. <hi>Pigeons</hi> annd Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> Eſtates to her Brother <hi>Edward Thorold,</hi> a ſhallow harmleſſe creature of himſelf, whom ſhe had ſent for out of <hi>Lincoln-ſhire</hi> to ſupply that part; her Trade being juſt like the Cut-purſes, that when he hath done his feat in a throng, he hath his bone-ſetters at hand to receive the Purſe and convey it away.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Coleborn</hi> had not been there long, but he extremly diſlikes both his entertainers and entertainment, and was often heard ſay with much paſſion, Oh that I were out of this houſe, theſe be ſtrange women! I ſuppoſe he meant in <hi>Solomons</hi> ſenſe; Theſe women (quoth he) are a deluſion, pray let me go to <hi>Betty,</hi> (a kinſwoman he had at <hi>Darking</hi>) but M ſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> kept him ſo long vexing his heart with her Conveyances and Aſſignments, that he could not be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but there expired to the ſhame and grief of all his friends; many of whom (for the very diſlike of that infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous houſe) would not come to his burial; and to the wonder of all men that ſo Politick a man as Mr. <hi>Coleborn</hi> ſhould ſuffer himſelf, in that laſt act of his Life, to be ſo <hi>Trepand</hi> into his Grave.</p>
            <p>Preſently after Mr. <hi>Coleborns</hi> Death, came Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> to Town, who appears like one from another world, having with much patience for four years born all his Wives inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, and ſeeing no amendment, but that every day ſhe grew more violent and miſchievous, (as appeared by the late ruine of Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> and his Children, and now awakened with his own wrongs, and the cryes of Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) he reſolves once more to take her into his cuſtody, and try if he can yoke this untamed Heifer: in ſhort, he appears with a Coach and four Horſes, and half a dozen
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118634:8"/> Servants, and having ſufficient authority, enters this Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons den, ſeizes and fairly conducts her into the Coach, and ſo carries her into the Country to his houſe; all the ſtreet looking on, and rejoycing at the riddance (as they hoped) of ſuch a troubleſome neighbor.</p>
            <p>To tell you her behaviour by the way, her throwing a glaſs of Wine into Mr. <hi>Pigeons</hi> Brothers face, while ſhe bowed and made ſhew as if ſhe would drink to him; her crying Murther, and accuſing her ſelf to have ſpoke Treaſon againſt the Lord Protector; her confeſſing her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Whore, and deſiring the Juſtice to ſend her to <hi>Bridewel;</hi> her affirming Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> to be none of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and Doctor <hi>Homes</hi> that married them, a knave: and many other ſuch freaks, would be tedious: But this I muſt not omit, at her firſt nights lodging on the way, Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> took her in private, and began to this effect; Wife (quoth he) have we not yet plaid the fools enough, ſhall we yet proceed in theſe ſcandalous conteſtations, making our ſelves Town talk, ſo that our Children, when grown up, will be aſhamed to own us for their Parents. When ſhe preſently replied, Are you in earneſt, would you have a Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, fall down at my feet and ask me forgiveneſſe. This, and ſuch-like, was her behaviour. In ſhort, a Juſtice of the Peace, at her requeſt, undertook to draw up an Award be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, the ſubſtance whereof was, That whereas ſhe denyed and diſclaimed Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> for her Husband, and no hopes of Reconciliation, he Awarded Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> his Land again, and 500. l. in Money, part of his former eſtate; and ſhe to have liberty to return to <hi>London,</hi> and live from Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> till they can better agree.</p>
            <p>But now Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> Children ſeing all deſperate, their Father deaf to all perſwaſions, Reſolve at laſt to Petition His Highneſſe the Lord Protector, who was pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Buſineſſe to ſeveral worthy Gentlemen in the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough of <hi>Southwark;</hi> who preſently ſummon Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> and his Women before them; where, to avoid repetition, the ſubſtance of all the former Printed Relation was fully proved, in ſo much that Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> ſeeing how things were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118634:9"/> likely to go, went home and preſently took his Bed, from whence he never roſe more: his ſickneſſe cauſed ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion of this Examination, and indeed many wayes gave great ſeeming advantage to the Women as you ſhall ſee; and if formerly in his health they plyed him with their peſtilent flatteries, now more than ever; ſo that for ſix or eight dayes before his death, they were ſcarce an hour ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (one or other of them) from his Bed-ſide, with great expreſſions of ſeeming tenderneſſe to him, yet ſcarce ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Children to look upon him; and when at any time any of them came to ſee him, and with bleeding affections minded him of his Spiritual Eſtate, then, Pray forbear, you trouble your Father, he would fain take his reſt; Dear Sir, Do they not trouble you? And knowing that of a long time they had ſo tutored him, that he durſt not anſwer but as they dictated to him; Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> would ſay, Mr. <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win,</hi> Have I ever wronged you, is it we or your Children that have ruined you? And then comes <hi>Mehetabel,</hi> Dear Sir, Speak as in the ſight of God, was I ever Naught with you? was I ever Contracted to you? Thus would they, eſpecially, before ſuch perſons as they thought for their purpoſe, worry this poor dying man, making him ſpend his laſt breath (that ſhould have been ſpent in making his peace with God) in juſtifying of their wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>The laſt of <hi>December,</hi> 1655. he departed this life; ſo ſoon as he was dead, Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> ſends for his Children to know if they would bury him; and if not, ſhe would: They asked, Who had his Eſtate? She replied, Alas! He hath not left one penny: all here is mine. In ſhort, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Children were robb'd of all: they agreed, and ſo told her, That they would bury him. And Miſtris <hi>Vernon</hi> in her haſte ſaid, If we bury him, we will know how he came by his death. This word (it ſeems) ſtuck with Miſtris <hi>Pigeon,</hi> and therefore contrary to this agreement, at Nine of the Clock that night, ſhe ſends them word, That ſhe had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got her ſelf, and now remembred that Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> had charged her upon his death-bed, That none of his Children ſhould have any hand in his burial; and that if they came
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118634:9"/> to bury him, ſhe would oppoſe then: this alarmed the Children, who went that night (though very late) to the Juſtices of the Borough, from whom they obtained an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der requiring theſe Women to permit them quietly to have acceſſe to the Body, and perform ſuch offices as were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite. This Order Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> peremptorily before good witneſſe refuſed to obey: and while Mr. <hi>Vernon</hi> went to the Juſtices to acquaint them with this Contempt of their Order, and was now returned with the Conſtable, and their Warrant to apprehend and bring them before them, he finds <hi>Andrew</hi> and <hi>Thomas Goodwin</hi> in the Bayliffs hands, Arreſted Priſoners, for Treſpaſſe of coming upon Miſtris <hi>Pigeons</hi> pretended Ground, and coming to the houſe, finds the doors barricadoed up, and a peremptory refuſal to obey either the Officer or the Warrant: and here I cannot but affirm, That I believe Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> died not a natural death, and omitting what might be charged upon them by altering his Diet from wholeſome Kitchin-food to Sage-Ale, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malade, ſtrong Extracts, which though in this kind ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed may be good, yet being turned to a conſtant Diet muſt needs deſtroy Nature and burn up the radical moyſture of his body; inſomuch that his Apothecary, a judicious skilful man affirmed to me that thoſe excellent Cordials he gave him in his ſickneſſe, revived him no more than cold water. I ſay omitting all this, I judge they were yet more directly inſtrumental to his death by uſing ſome wicked practiſe upon him to deſtroy him; and there are theſe ſigns, Firſt, That for three or four dayes before his death he conſtantly complained of a great burning in his bowels: Secondly, His frequent violent retchings to vomit, in one of which retching fits he died; both apparent ſigns of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: that which ſeems to confirm this, is their refuſing to ſuffer his Children to bury him, or to ſee the Body, though back'd with the Magiſtrates Authority. After they once heard their intention to have the Body Diſſected, 'tis true, the third day after his death, they ſent to the Doctor to tell him that he might come and viſit the Body outwardly, but by no means they would not have it opened and Diſſected:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118634:10"/> if you ask why they ſhould ſo wickedly rid themſelves of their old friend who loved them ſo dearly to his laſt? I anſwer firſt, the trade was now utterly loſt and henceforth he could be but a cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g and a reproach to them: Secondly, the trade being gone, and he having no maintenance but from the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous churliſh hands of Mrs <hi>Pigeon;</hi> &amp; his Children ſtill fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing him with their prayrs, he might come to have his eyes opened. But laſtly, Mrs <hi>Pigeons</hi> great fear was, that now that the whole project was before the Commiſſioners in Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, who being judicious quick-ſighted-Gentlemen, and Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> being a ſhallow weak man, and perhaps exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined privately, might ſo ill manage h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Defence as might ſpoyle all; of which ſhe had a ſhrewd example the firſt day of Examination, where when ſhe was accuſed by Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> to have brought old Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> ſix years agone to the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wſe,</hi> and there cauſed him to make his Will, by which he gave by her direction 600. l. to her Siſter <hi>Jones;</hi> which when Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> was Examined upon, ſhe with dreadful aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verations and appeals to God, utterly denied; ſaying it was lyes in every circumſtance: yet when Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> who by reaſon of his deafneſſe ſcarce heard what they ſaid, was Examined, whether it were ſo or no, he Confeſſed all, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by putting a deadly affront upon Miſtris <hi>Pigeon:</hi> adde to this their being conſtantly at his Bed-ſide in his ſickneſſe, not ſuffering, as I ſaid, his Children ſcarce to ſpeak to him; and at one time warning Miſtris <hi>Vernon,</hi> while ſhe was carefully attending her Father, to go off the ground, or they would Arreſt her Husband for Treſpaſſe, whereby they had oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to do what they would, and they (ſhe-Doctors or Quack-ſalvers, whereof they have both for many years made profeſſion) preſcribing Phyſick as confidently as if they were Members of the Colledge: Theſe are ſome grounds of my belief, which the Reader may judge of, and the full diſcovery thereof I refer to the great Day. But to return; The door being faſt barred up, and the old man nailed in his Coffin, miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> once again falls to new devices. The third day at night, when the body began now to putrifie,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118634:10"/> ſhe ſends meſſenger after meſſenger at ten of the Clock at night to the Children, requiring them to come and bury the Body, or it ſhould for good and all remain unburied: But they being now adviſed by the Magiſtrate not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, and by the Doctor that it was too late to make Diſſection, the thing they aimed at, they poſitively refuſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by this proffer miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> thinks to take off all ſuſpition of his death, and now ſeeing this Project fail, ſhe reſolves on the ſudden to bury him in ſtate: ſhe invites all the chief of the Pariſh; and amongſt the reſt, forgets not the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful Commiſſioners, giving them to underſtand they ſhould all be ſerved with Gold Rings and Gloves: but they all, except Mr. <hi>Samuel Hyghland,</hi> (who preſently bit at the bait) with juſt ſcorn rejected this bribing Device: Seventy or Eighty Rings are provided: The Poſie by miſtris <hi>Pigeons</hi> device out of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Sown in diſhonor, raiſed in glory.</hi> She can for all purpoſes make uſe of abuſed Scripture to colour her ſin, though at other times ſhe ſaith, ſhe cares not if the Bible were burnt, as was proved; but let any man look on the Context, and ſee any Expoſition that ever was made upon that Scripture, they will find the Apoſtle meant not the leaſt in her ſenſe, but ſpeaks only of the Body, which by death is become a loathſome ſpectacle devoid of all beauty and luſtre. There is another text which with a little of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris <hi>Pigeons</hi> ſtrayning, would have done better, viz. <hi>His death to me is Gain.</hi> What think you miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> after you had cheated a ſhallow old man of an Eſtate of 2000. l. and when he could do you no more drudgery, to go, or be ſent out of the world, then a parcel of fine Gold Rings, with <hi>Mors mihi lucrum,</hi> would it not have argued your ingenuity? Well, the Fourth day at night was the burial: and Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> Children, conſidering all the fore-mentioned paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, though invited, refuſed to joyn with them that had brought their Father with ſo much diſgrace to the Grave, but went and attended the Corps at the Grave, which at laſt comes; and next the Corps, in a Coach, Mr. <hi>Hat,</hi> miſtris <hi>Pigeon,</hi> and miſtris <hi>Hat;</hi> whom Politick miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> brought with her to be her buckler and awe the people; ſhe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118634:11"/> having of late been ſeveral times aſſaulted by the Boyes, but now look to your ſelves, here is Mr. <hi>John Hat,</hi> the <hi>Guild-hall</hi> Atturney, that if you be uncivil ſhall make his Actions of Aſſault and Battery flie about your ears: yet the people railed upon them all the way, now and then ſaluting them with handfuls of kennel dirt; and I am perſwaded in that emotion of the people, had any of Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> Children but held up a finger, they had run great hazard of their lives; there as I am informed was Couſin <hi>Charles Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rold</hi> and his Lady, who followed not as the people after <hi>Abſolom,</hi> in the ſimplicity of their hearts, but in the ſimple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his underſtanding. As for <hi>Mehetabel,</hi> ſhe was ſo overcome with Paſſion, not of Grief for the loſſe of her dear friend, but of fear of the loſing her dear life that ſhe kept under lock and key at the Dye-houſe: indeed had ſhe appeared, I think the beſt of her bargain would have been to be ſent to gage the depth of the mud in the mill-pond.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> buried, the Commiſsioners proceed to a finall Examination of the Buſineſſe; and upon the whole, finding clearly how they had cheated Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> and all his children, they made a Propoſition to M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
               <hi>Pigeon,</hi> That wheras ſhe pretended the Eſtate hers; firſt, by Aſſignment to Mr. <hi>Coleborn</hi> for her uſe; &amp; then, by his Aſſignment to her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Thorold;</hi> by which, as Mr. <hi>Hat</hi> then pleaded for her, ſhe had a legal Title at Law, which he enforced with all his <hi>Guild-hall</hi> Rethorike, till the Commiſſioners commanded him out of doors, that if ſhe would deliver up the Eſtate as it was when ſhe invaded it, and give a true Accompt as well of her Receipts as Diſburſments, they would repay her all her Charges with 100. l. advantage: which ſhe with ſcorn refuſed, ſaying, It was hers by Law, and by Law ſhe would keep it. So the Examination ended, and the Worſhipful Commiſſioners, according to what was alleaged and proved, drew up a Report of the Caſe to His Highneſs, which is here annexed verbatim, with the Atteſtation of Mr. <hi>Kiffins</hi> Church, and Mr. <hi>Pigeons</hi> Affidavit.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:118634:11"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="report">
                        <head>The <hi>REPORT.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>ACcording to your Highneſs Command upon the Reference of Mr.</hi> Goodwins <hi>Childrens Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto us, we have ſeveral times Met, and called before us the Perſons concerned in the ſaid Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, Complainants, Deffendants, Witneſſes; We take leave upon the whole to ſubmit this Accompt unto your Highneſs, as the Reſult of our Conſciencies upon an impartial ſearch.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1.</hi> That there hath been juſt Scandal given to the People of God by the too familiar Converſe of <hi>Weſſel Goodwin</hi> (ſince deceaſed) and <hi>Mehetabel</hi> the Wife of <hi>Edward Jones,</hi> when being admoniſhed by the Elders of their reſpective Churches, yet after the ſaid admonitions, and promiſes on their parts of forbearance, they not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly came together as before, but juſtified their ſo doing; and that after the Excluſion of them from the Ordinances and Congregations, as is alledged in the Petition.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2.</hi> For a covering to the ſhame of this evil familiarity, there have been an agreement of Marriage contracted with the aſsiſtance of <hi>Elizabeth Pigeon,</hi> ſiſter to the ſaid <hi>Mehetabel,</hi> between Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> and Miſtris <hi>Jones</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and they have endeavoured to prove it lawful, notwithſtanding that Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> husband to the ſaid <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hetabel,</hi> be yet alive.</p>
                        <p n="3">
                           <hi>3.</hi> In Order to the gaining of Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> eſtate (which was the Deſign laid between them <hi>8.</hi> or <hi>9.</hi> years ſince) by the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Jones</hi> and Miſtris <hi>Pigeon,</hi> they found it requiſite to remove <hi>Andrew Goodwin,</hi> eldeſt Son of <hi>Weſſel Goodwin,</hi> ſetled upon Marriage in partner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with his Father in the Dye-houſe-ſtock and Trade;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118634:12"/> we ſay they Outed the ſaid <hi>Andrew</hi> by fraud and force in this manner; they brake open his Counting-houſe and Trunks, taking out thence his Accompts &amp; Books whereby he is diſabled to make good his Stock; then they brought an Accomptant to Ballance the Accompts between the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son, and to this Accomptant Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> proffered thirty pounds as a bribe to falſifie the Accompts that no eſtate might be found due to the ſaid <hi>Andrew,</hi> that ſo he might be caſt out of the ſaid partner-ſhip for the ends aforeſaid. Then they proceed to warn the ſaid <hi>Andrew</hi> out of the houſe; which he refuſing to obey, they brought in Bayliffs at midnight and brake open his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber door and took him by violence, Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by incouraging and abetting the Bayliffs who haled him thence to priſon; In which extremity the ſaid <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> was forced to confeſs a Judgment to one of his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, to whom he owed one hundred and thirty pounds, whereby part of the eſtate was taken in execution; which being by Miſtris <hi>Pigeons</hi> procurement appraiſed at a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry under rate, ſhe brought her friend in truſt to pay down the money; and by other ſubtile practiſes got poſſeſsion of that whole eſtate to the value of above fifteen hundred pounds, and by this means framing a kind of Title by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Law doth keep and diſpoſe of this eſtate at her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, defrauding thereby the Children, your Highneſs Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners.</p>
                        <p n="4">
                           <hi>4.</hi> That we did according to your Highneſs Advice endeavour to compoſe the whole buſineſs impartially ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to rules of Juſtice and Conſcience, profering to Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> (ſhe being the chief Patroneſs, Contriver, and Manager of this Project) upon her giving us a true Accompt of all her Disburſments upon the eſtate to repay her all with an advantage.</p>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118634:12"/>
                        <p>But all our tenders in behalf of the wronged Petitioners were by her rejected with ſcorn, ſhe pleading her preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Title and Property by Law.</p>
                        <p>Now laſtly, Whereas your Highneſs requireth our Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in this Caſe, we take leave in this our capacity to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That the merits and matter of the Petition are true, and the Petitioners greatly injured, not only by the ſaid <hi>Weſſel,</hi> but principally by the two Siſters, Miſtris <hi>Jones</hi> and Miſtris <hi>Pigeon,</hi> who had wholly captivated the weak underſtanding and affections of the ſaid old Mr. <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi> even to his death, and now impudently poſſeſs the whole eſtate; And our Opinion further is, That it were a righteous thing in the ſight of God and man to repair this loſs and injuries upon the ſaid eſtate, and the Uſurpers of it; yea, and that ſomething exemplarily penal be inflicted upon theſe Women, that others may be deterred from the like attempts.</p>
                        <p>And ſeeing your Petitioners are utterly diſabled to wage Law, their Adverſaries having the Eſtate, we conceive it a moſt Honorable Work that your Highneſs interpoſe your Authority, that ſome compendious way be taken to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine this buſineſs.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Chriſtopher Searle.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>William Cooper.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Cor. Cook.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Hardwick.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <opener>
                              <dateline>
                                 <hi>White-hall,</hi> 
                                 <date>
                                    <hi>March</hi> 14. 1655.</date>
                              </dateline>
                           </opener>
                           <p>His Highneſs referreth this Report to the ſpeedy and ſpecial Conſideration and Order of His Highneſſes Privy Council.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Intr. Nath. Bacon.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </postscript>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:118634:13"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="attestation">
                        <head>The Atteſtation of Mr. <hi>Kiffin's</hi> Church.</head>
                        <p>THe Church having by ſeveral Witneſſes heard that Mrs. <hi>Jones</hi> did frequently give entertainment to one Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> did make further enquiry thereinto by ſome Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren appointed to that end, who ſpeaking to her about it, received this Anſwer, That it was only upon a Chriſtian ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, they being long acquainted together, having at that time no particular proof of any thing, did at preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt any further dealing with her, only ordered ſome Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that lived neareſt her to exerciſe more then ordinary watchfulneſs over her; and after ſome time we by them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that ſhe had diſpoſſeſſed her Husband <hi>Jones</hi> of all he had, and was gone into the Country and Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> with her; and making further enquiry into her converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in that matter, had proof that ſhe did uſe very familiar unſeemly carriages to Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> and promiſed that if all things were clear, ſhe would take him to be her Husband; which words and carriages ſhe being dealt withal in the Church for, ſhe denied the carriages, but confeſſed ſhe did uſe words to him to that effect, and with many tears preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her condition to the Church, touching the evil conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of her Husband <hi>Jones;</hi> and did promiſe that for time to come, ſhe would not frequent the company of Mr. <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win;</hi> upon which promiſe the Church ſolemnly admoniſhed her, and ſo left it: not long after we underſtood that Miſtris <hi>Jones</hi> did more frequently then ever we heard before, give entertainment to Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> he being daily at her houſe, &amp; very late at night, if not all night, which neighbors taking notice of, took occaſion thereby to ſpeak very reproachfully of Profeſſion, to the grief of ſeveral of our Members which lived near her; who reporting the ſame to the Church, ſhe was ſent for by the Church: and when ſhe came and was charged with this Scandalous Converſation, together with her breach of Promiſe, ſhe then laboured to juſtifie her Practiſe; and told the Church, That ſhe had been with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral learned Divines, who had given in their Opinions that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118634:13"/> ſhe was free from the Law of her firſt Husband by the Law of God: We finding her obſtinate in the evils ſhe was charged withal, and reſolved to go on in the ſame without any regard to the honour of God, ſcandal of Religion, or former Engagement, did judge it our duty to caſt her out of the Church, which accordingly was done for the aboveſaid evils. Witneſs our Hands,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>George Gosfright.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>William Angel.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>William Warren.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Sowdin.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>William Kiffen.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Battey.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But to draw to a Concluſion, Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> Children pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the Report, and preſent it to His Highneſs with all the Commiſſioners hands, except Mr. <hi>Highland,</hi> who refuſed to ſubſcribe, not (as he affirmed before good witneſs) that he doubted the Fraud, but queſtioned the matter of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal; now hereby hangs a tale, but it is an old one, and therefore I forbear. Now the Children having preſented the Report to his Highneſs, who expreſſed a high Reſentment of it, and commanded an extraordinary Order to be drawn referring it to the ſpeedy and ſpecial care of his Highneſs privy Council; who after two months attendance by the Children, were pleaſed to caſt it out, and refer them to the Law: And the Children conſidering Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> is in Poſſeſſion, and they ruined and ſtript of all, do refer it to the Great Judge of Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <p>Thus you have ſeen Miſtris <hi>Pigeon</hi> Rampant in all her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which hath ſince emboldened her to a new ſtrange at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt: For obſerving Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> very active to aſſiſt Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> Children both before the Commiſſioners, and at <hi>White-hal,</hi> firſt ſhe attempts him by M <hi>Hat,</hi> who adviſed him in preſence of good witneſs, not to meddle to aſſiſt thoſe beggarly people <hi>Goodwins</hi> Children; but ſeeing Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> out of an honeſt ſence of their wrongs, not to be taken off, he then threatned him with the Gaol: but Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> ſtill purſuing the honeſt Cauſe of the Children, they conſult and at laſt reſolve upon an old Writ of ſpecial <hi>Supplicavit,</hi> long ſince taken out of the <hi>Chancery</hi> upon articles that Mrs. <hi>Pigeon</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118634:14"/> and her bold Maid <hi>Mary Maſon,</hi> and one Miſtris <hi>Newton</hi> had delivered upon Oath; in which they affirm, That ſhe had been grievouſly beaten by Mr. <hi>Pigeon (not half enough)</hi> and that ſhe went in danger of her life: and upon theſe Articles they procured the Writ; which directed to the Sheriffs, they iſſue out a Warrant for Mr. <hi>Pigeons</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion: this they deliver to a hair-braind Sergeant one Capt. <hi>Bunne,</hi> whom they inſtruct; and he contrary to the Warrant which directed him to take Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> and carry him before the next Juſtice, and there that he put in ſecurity for the Peace, and ſo be diſcharged: But Cap. <hi>Bunne</hi> who now is in the bryars for his pains, refuſing to carry him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Magiſtrate, throws him into Priſon, where Mr. <hi>Pigeon</hi> having put in Bayl, was Releaſed, and is now in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of the Diſcharge of the Writ, and ſo of his Bayl.</p>
            <p>Here follows the Copies of ſeveral Letters written by <hi>Mrs. Jones</hi> and <hi>Mrs. Pigeon</hi> to old <hi>Mr. Goodwin,</hi> as they were found in his Study after his death; which Letters, with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Locks of <hi>Mrs. Jones</hi> her Hair, remain in the hands of <hi>Mr. Samuel Vernon</hi> at the lower end of St. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Acts,</hi> for all that deſire to peruſe; and good proof up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath, that theſe Letters are their own hand-writing.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Firſt is a Letter from <hi>Mrs. Lydia Walſal,</hi> the elder Siſter to theſe Women, and late Wife to Doctor <hi>Walſal</hi> of <hi>Sandy</hi> in <hi>Bedfordſhire</hi> directed to <hi>Mr. Goodwin.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My very much eſteemed good Brother,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am very glad to hear of your health, and the health of yours: but ſorry to hear your oppreſsion of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: the Lord for his Chriſts ſake, either increaſe ſtrength, or take off trouble. Brother, I much thank you for your good leave to enjoy my good Siſter, by whoſe means I have received eaſe: I hope I ſhall find more good: and beſides I am not yet ſatisfied with her good Company, and therefore beg your leave that I may
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118634:14"/> enjoy her one week more at leaſt, that we may be refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed each by other, for hitherto my poor dear Siſter hath done nothing but toyled:<note place="margin">☞</note> 
                     <hi>If you receive her two inches leſs in the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e, who can help it?</hi> For up be-time ſhe will, and to her day-labour, but her Wages muſt come from Heaven, for I can never requite her Love and pains: My Husband and good Siſter remember their Loves.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your ever loving Siſter, <hi>Lydia Walſal.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Can any other Inference be made from this, than that <hi>Mrs Jones</hi> was either <hi>Mr. Goodwins</hi> Wife, which (for that her Husband is yet alive) ſhe cannot lawfully be or his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubine; ſuch Embraces can hardly allow any other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: but <hi>Mrs. Pigeons</hi> diſtinction ſalves all; <hi>Mr.</hi> Jones <hi>is her Husband by the unjuſt Law of man, and Mr.</hi> Goodwin <hi>her Husband in the ſight of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The next is from <hi>Mrs Jones.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HOnoured Sir, I have been much troubled about my leaving you, and could wiſh my ſelf with you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain if I could, becauſe I was never-more reſtleſſe than now: let me receive a Word or two from you, it may be that may a little ſatisfie me, which ſhall for ever engage me to you.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your faithful friend, <hi>Mehetubal Jones.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This agrees with the former from <hi>Mrs. Walſal,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm there was a ſecret union between them.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Another from <hi>Mrs. Jones,</hi> and hath for Superſcription, <hi>To my dear Siſter, Mrs.</hi> Montague <hi>at</hi> Ockingham; but the in-ſide Contents are,</head>
                  <p>GOod Mr. <hi>Goodwin.</hi> I deſire to hear how you do, and how you have digeſted your double meat of two
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118634:15"/> Gooſes: truly one will ſtick by you longer than I hope the other will ſtick in your ſtomack: however the ribs of one is devoured by you, yet the other will ſtick by the ribs, and be as the rib taken forth of the left-ſide, ever before you, bone of your bone and fleſh of your fleſh: ſo I reſt.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Yours to ſerve you, <hi>Mehetabel Jones.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This wants a Commentary in a Letter written by <hi>Mrs. Mountague,</hi> there is mention of a Gooſe ſent as a preſent to be eaten by the two Siſters and <hi>Mr. Goodwin,</hi> it ſhould ſeem in their merriment <hi>Mr. Goodwin</hi> jeſtingly called <hi>Mrs. Jones</hi> Gooſe, a word frequent with him; and upon this <hi>Mrs. Jones</hi> writes this Letter, and now riddle my riddle.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A Fourth Letter from her ſayes,</head>
                  <p>GOod Brother, I had a weariſome journey: yet if I could have poſsibly got my Siſters leave, I had come to <hi>London</hi> as this day: truly my heart is there; for I am willing as the Lord hath commanded, to help to bear your burthen more then formerly: having recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a little breath, I am willing to draw in this eaſie yoke of Chriſt, if it muſt be ſo, but humbly beſeech him to make it ſomewhat eaſier than it hath been: <hi>viz. <hi>When ſhe lived with her Husband</hi> Jones:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☞</note> 
                     <hi>here is adultery and blaſphemy together. The reſt of this Letter is a parcel of Inſtructions in a Religious dreſſe, whereby ſhe captivated the ſilly old man; but being tedious and impertinent, I omit them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>In a Fifth ſhe ſaith,</head>
                  <p>HOnoured Sir, I wiſh I could conveniently write at this time to you: but I thought fit to let you know, That I fear it is intended that your Couſin <hi>Arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong</hi> ſhall ſerve in <hi>Richards</hi> place. I doubt not but the Lord will give you wiſdom and directions in all things; which ſhall be the Prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your faithful friend till death, <hi>Mehetabel Jones.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118634:15"/>
            <p>This Letter was written ſeven years agone, by which you ſee they governed all at the Dye-houſe long before they came there; for a beck from her, or her Siſter, was a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to him; indeed <hi>Richard Armſtrong</hi> was one that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their practiſes upon <hi>Mr. Goodwin,</hi> and therefore though an excellent Workman, muſt not be entertained.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>And that you may further ſee how they governed him, in a Sixth ſhe ſaith,</head>
                  <p>SIR, if any one whoſoever ſhould ſend for you, or come to ſpeak with you, know they do it to intrap you: I pray if ſo, go not to them, till you come to me: but if you hear not from any, I ſhall not look for you till to morrow in the afternoon.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This is the ſame hand, but hath neither Super, nor Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, was ever poor man ſo barnacled with a cunning Strumpet: let the buſineſſe be of what conſequence ſoever, he muſt not ſpeak with any till he have conſulted with her, and have her leave; it ſhould appear that ſome of her Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guery was now in danger of diſcovery.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>In a Seventh, ſhe ſayes,</head>
                  <p>HOnoured Sir, The Lord hath made our journey very comfortable: but now I fear our return will be imbittered by the want of that, which of all earthly things is moſt deſired, <hi>viz. <hi>Mr. Goodwins company:</hi>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">☜</note> It will not be convenient for us to come to you in regard of many ſatisfactory reaſons which I can give you: Dear Sir, let us ſee you.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>And in a Poſt-ſcript <hi>Mrs. Pigeon</hi> writes thus,</head>
                  <p>SIR, Now God hath put you to the Tryal of the ſtrength you thought you had: you ſaid you could ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Will of God though it ſhould be the loſſe of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118634:16"/> your deareſt Friend <hi>(viz <hi>her Siſter</hi> Jones)</hi> now therefore chear up,<note place="margin">☞</note> and know this ſtroak is the love and good will of our dear Father: I need ſay no more.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Do you not think that Dame <hi>Celeſtina,</hi> the famous Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Bawd, was a Fool in compariſon of <hi>Mrs. Pigeon?</hi> ſhe wanted this rare art of Canting in a Religious tone: the ſum of all is, That about this time <hi>Mrs. Jones</hi> by the Juſtices and <hi>Mr. Kiffins</hi> Church, was warned out of <hi>Mr. Goodwins</hi> company, and had engaged to them to refrain it becauſe of the Scandal. Now ſee how <hi>Mrs. Pigeon</hi> can dreſs this trade of Harlotry, thereby to caiole the conſcience of this deluded old man.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Eighth from <hi>Mrs. Jones.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WOrthy Sir, whom I do truly honor, let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you have a ſpecial care of taking cold, or working to morrow: our next neighbor is dead of a looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, conſider your age and weakneſſe. I have been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill, but am ſomething better: ſince I heard from you I have ſent you a Waſtcoat, pray ſend me word if you will wear it. I exceedingly fear your falling into a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, if you take pains before you have recovered your ſtrength.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your faithful friend, <hi>M. Jones.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Who would not part with Eſtate, Credit, Children, Friends, a good Conſcience and all, to keep ſuch a friend in a corner? So truly ſaith <hi>Solomon, The lips of a ſtrange Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man drop as a honey Comb, and her mouth is more ſoft than oyl.</hi> The tongues of theſe two Siſters being tipt with, Dear Sir; Honoured Sir; Precious Sir; and pretending to admire his wiſedom, while they laugh in their ſleeves to ſee his extreme weakneſſe and credulity. But by theſe arts they held him faſt and were admired, while his Children and friends that deale plainly with him, were reviled and ſcorned.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118634:16"/>
                  <head>Yet again this Cogging Huſwife in a Ninth.</head>
                  <p>EVer honored Sir, Dear Brother, I humbly beſeech you not to be offended at my going ſo ſuddenly away, for the truth is, I was neceſsitated to go to the farther end of the Garden,<note place="margin">☜</note> 
                     <hi>(viz. The Houſe of Office)</hi> and then my Siſter <hi>Mountague</hi> fell inſtantly ſick, ſo ſick that ſhe thought ſhe ſhould have died, ſo that I was forced to be with her a little, but inſtantly I came down: Sir, I beſeech you that I may ſpeak with you: pleaſe not to trouble your ſelf for any thing whatſoever: for if you know as much as I, you would rejoyce: Take heed of your Son <hi>Andrew.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Thus Harlots and Hypocrites diſcover their rotten hearts while they over do: Is not this a ſtrange obſequiouſneſs that <hi>Mrs. Jones</hi> cannot go to unburthen Nature but ſhe muſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologize for it: What a dutiful Concubine is <hi>Mr. Goodwin</hi> like to have. But all this Diſſembling is but to prepare him for the cloſe, to alienate him from his children.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Once again in a Tenth Letter.</head>
                  <p>SIR, I hear that Mr. <hi>Tarleton</hi> is to be to morrow at Mr. <hi>Vernons;</hi> I beſeech you give me leave to put you in remembrance of your former wiſe diſcreet Carriage, never to be forgotten, which was when you have been in the like Surpriſal: Firſt, A Reſerved ſtrangeneſſe: Secondly, Not to enter the Lifts of Argument: Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, If they come directly upon you, either to intrap you, or elſe to Examine or Charge you with that which you are not willing to diſcloſe, or juſtifie to them the lawfulneſs of <hi>(viz. The Adulterous Contract with her)</hi> then I have obſerved your Serpentine wiſdom to daunt their boldneſs with a ſeeming angry diſpleaſure,<note place="margin">☜</note> fenced with Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſeek Wiſdom from the Wiſe and wonderful Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor, in ſuch matters wherein his Glory and your good
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118634:17"/> is ſo nearly concerned,<note place="margin">☞</note> 
                     <hi>(viz. His Marriage with her)</hi> Sir, this hath been the Armor wherewith the Lord hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed all their <hi>Goliahs,</hi> Counſels, Plots, and Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems: I hope a Monitor will be doubly welcome to you, which brings no Reproof, but an Olive-branch, a Remembrance, or Memorial of your former Vertues: for ſuch a friend I remain,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Mehetabel Jones.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Was there ever ſuch a Trepan, ſuch glavering in a bold diſſembling Woman, and ſuch obtuſe folly in an old man; at one time ſhe tells him there hath not lived a wiſer man than he ſince King <hi>Solomon:</hi> and in this rabble of impudent non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe of <hi>Serpentine wiſdom, and diſcreet Carriage, never to be forgotten;</hi> and yet thus laden with deep underſtanding, he muſt have an inchanted pad-lock hung upon his lips, not be truſted to utter one word: and being thus clawed with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of wiſdom, as it is ſtrange to ſee how greedily weak and ſhallow perſons do affect to be accompted wiſe; and this was one of the ſnares they held him faſt with: you would wonder how exactly he would follow thoſe directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Urge what you would, ask him twenty queſtions, not a word. At this very meeting, being earneſtly preſſed about the Contract with this Woman, by my ſelf and others; <hi>Mr. Goodwin,</hi> Are you married to miſtris <hi>Jones?</hi> are you Contracted to her? and ſuch queſtions as he was not willing to diſcloſe to us, or juſtifie the lawfulneſſe of them, as <hi>Mrs. Jones</hi> ſaith, With a Reſerved ſtrangeneſs, and a ſeeming an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry diſpleaſure, fenced with Reſolution to be wholly guided by <hi>Mrs Jones,</hi> his wiſe and wonderful Counſellour, it being a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter that ſo nearly concerned; their being preſerved from ſhameful Pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhment; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d he with ſilence and frowns anſwer all our demands: So that you would have thought him inchanted.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:118634:17"/>
                  <head>The Eleventh is a Copy of a Letter written with <hi>Mrs. Jones</hi> own hand, with direction to <hi>Mr. Goodwin</hi> to tranſcribe, and ſend it to her Siſter <hi>Pigeon</hi> as from himſelf, and begins thus,</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Miſtris <hi>Pigeon,</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THrough the unuſual, unheard of, unnatural dealing of my Children, who joyning with my Son <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew,</hi> and uſing his Name and Power, which Power was given him for his and my Good, to be uſed for the good of the Trade: But he drawn aſide by his own evil Heart, and the temptations of Satan, and ſeduced and ſeconded by his wicked Brethren and Siſters, whom the Prince of Darkneſs hath uſed as his Inſtruments to bring upon me all theſe ſore Calamities as are viſible this day, which as I think I may ſay my Caſe is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out compare, &amp; that in my old age (excepting <hi>Davids</hi> and <hi>Jobs</hi>) But not to reaſon with fleſh and blood, in that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I would ſay it were far better to have them taken away Obedient Children, then to have them live as <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoloms</hi> as mine does, and their Printed Libels does wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (God knowing my innocence, to whom I appeal as a Righteous Iudge) But I leave all this as a long pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis and come to the Buſineſs: When they were thus ſuffered to be Scourges, Scourges ſaid I, nay Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Scorpions, endeavoring to eat out the Bowels from whence they proceeded, then the Lord God uſed you as the only means to keep me from a viſible Ruine, as far as the eye of Reaſon could reach: Now therefore my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is, if you have any farther thoughts towards me, through your love and tenderneſs, That you would not do any thing for me <hi>in any of my Childrens Names</hi> how O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient ſoever at preſent:<note place="margin">☜</note> for I had far more Cauſe of Hopes of thoſe that have endeavored my Ruine then hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto of <hi>James:</hi> I therefore deſire that you would do that which you ſhall do for me <hi>in thoſe Names that you can Truſt and Confide,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☜</note> neither ſhall I now nominate any for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118634:18"/> ſufficient Reaſons known to my ſelf <hi>(viz. to Mrs. <hi>Jones</hi>)</hi> and having found your faithfulneſs all along, I leave to you,<note place="margin">☞</note> deſiring <hi>you to Nominate</hi> whom you ſhall think fit: only this I deſire, That the Power I have formerly had in the Houſe I now dwell in, may be continued to me, and Notice given me when things are ſettled: and I ſhall leave it in Writing how my Deſire is, That that Eſtate I ſhall have, ſhall be Diſpoſed of after my Death: for which, I ſhall have great Cauſe to Remain,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your thankful Friend.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter is a Compendium of all the Villany theſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have acted; where firſt you plainly ſee how they go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned this poor weak man at their pleaſure, making him own all their wicked Projects and Deſigns, as if they were his own Deſires. See here how they to accompliſh their own purpoſe the better, to fil his heart with bitterneſs againſt all his Children: No marvel when his Daughter <hi>Vernon</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times upon her knees with tears in her eyes, hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought him to refrain the ſcandalous Society of theſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſhe could obtain no better anſwer then, You are a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Cham:</hi> And thus did they wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him continually againſt them, that ſo they might poſſeſſe him and all his Eſtate. Again, ſee with what Atheiſtical boldneſs they direct him to appeal to God of his innocency, when their own hand Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting diſcovers to all the world, that the bottom was an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Contract with <hi>Mrs. Jones,</hi> and manifeſt injuſtice and cruelty to all his Children; by their appointment ſtripping them of that which by the Law of God and of Nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to them: and ſee how blaſphemouſly they paint all this with Religion. Again, ſee how they make him groſly Lye, to pleaſure and juſtifie them, when they had been eight years plotting to cheat him of all his Eſtate, and have now effected it; then muſt this poor beſotted Creature tell <hi>Mrs. Pigeon,</hi> That the Lord God raiſed her to keep him from Ruine: This is the ſublime Art of Trepanning, to gull a man of an Eſtate of 2000. l. and then make him write a long E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of Gratulation, and ſlaviſh Acknowledgement of her
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118634:18"/> Love and tenderneſs. Here alſo you plainly ſee <hi>James Goodwin</hi> was uſed as a meer Property; he muſt (a ſilly young School-Boy, though to his utter Ruine, the ſcandal of Religion) be married to <hi>Lydda Jones,</hi> a ſhe Babby, that ſo theſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may have a door opened to get in, and throw out <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> and his Father, and poſſeſſe all the Eſtate: and this no ſooner done, but <hi>Mrs. Pigeon</hi> calls him Loggerhead and Puppy; and <hi>Mrs. Jones</hi> his Mother directs his Father to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt him in this Letter to <hi>Mrs. Pigeon.</hi> You ſee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo how ſhe directs <hi>Mr. Goodwin</hi> to beg of <hi>Mrs. Pigeon</hi> that as ſhe had hitherto cheated him, ſo ſhe would go on and perfect this model of Theevery. Laſtly, you ſee what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion <hi>Mrs. Jones</hi> makes, that nothing after his Death may come to his Children, he muſt reſerve a Power in the houſe, that at his death he may bequeath it to her, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly he performed by his Nuncupative Will on his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, deſiring the Houſe might go to his dear Siſter <hi>Jones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now having made him do all this dutiful drudgery, to make him amends, ſhe writes him a Love Letter which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins thus.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MY D. P. H. <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </hi> My dear precious Heart: My <hi>D. K. H. <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </hi> My dear kind Heart, I much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee you, which let me when your firſt opportunity will permit, and ſpare ſo much time from your ſleep while as to write a large Epiſtle, not in Characters, but at large in long-hand, not with <hi>H.</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> till death: but in words at large and full, ſo full, as may put me fully in a whole Sheet filled on both ſides, which ſhall be more welcome to me than my Winding-ſhéet, and be the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger your ſelf,<note place="margin">☜</note> 
                     <hi>(elſe how ſhall the Sheet be filled on both ſides?)</hi> ſo you ſhall not fear miſcarrying: I have wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch Shéets long: and truly, now I long for ſuch a Shéet brought with your hand, which ſhall be moſt kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly welcome: and for which if you bring, I ſhall ever be yours till death.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter is ſubject to a double conſtruction, if in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity you will take the literal meaning, why does ſhe ſo urge
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118634:19"/> over and over for him to come in perſon; but I leave every man to his freedom, and make the beſt of it you can; it is ſtark naught, and wicked.</p>
            <p>And further, that the old man may ſee ſhe is all on flame in Love to him, ſhe is turned Poet, and inſpired with a Bottle of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge-Ale, ſhe greets him in theſe ſtrains.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <l>We have drunk your Ale, and for it ſend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>the commendations of your deareſt friend;</l>
                        <l>although the liquor be but ſmall,</l>
                        <l>the givers Gift doth equal all.</l>
                        <l>This is the Gift which you did ſend,</l>
                        <l>grave pye-baked Sage-ale to your friend:</l>
                        <l>but as you ſent it in good part,</l>
                        <l>ſo drank it we, with all our heart.</l>
                        <l>In drinking it, we did remember</l>
                        <l>him that was the Bottle ſender.</l>
                        <l>If me you blame for want of wit,</l>
                        <l>it was the Ale that out with it.</l>
                        <l>And with the Bottle back I have ſent,</l>
                        <l>for him that wants more then is ſpent.</l>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Your Friend,</hi> Mehetabel Jones.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Who can blame poor <hi>Mr. Goodwin</hi> for telling his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Vernon,</hi> That his former Wife deſerved not to be named the ſame day with her, ſhe could not Poetiſe and ſcratch Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baldry Rhymns till they bleed again. Many other parcels of her venereous Poetry I finde, but being hob-nayl tattered ſtuffe I omit; only beg leave for one Sample more of her inchanting Madrigals; which with a parcel of her Hair richly perfumed (though all will not keep it from ſtinking) was found with the reſt; and thus it Chimes, forth:
<q>
                  <l>Accept this Bracelet from your friend,</l>
                  <l>the owner knows it is your due,</l>
                  <l>becauſe ſhe belongeth unto you.</l>
                  <l>This paper read, let it ſee the flame;</l>
                  <l>if you grant not this, you are to blame:</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:118634:19"/>
                  <l>For ſhe that writ it, would for you</l>
                  <l>burn paper, and her fingers too</l>
                  <l>to light your ſnuff; which ſhe has done,</l>
                  <l>and burnt both fingers and her thumbe,</l>
                  <l>Burn it, then your friend I will reſt;</l>
                  <l>if not, ſay not you love her beſt:</l>
                  <l>The hours I count, the minutes too,</l>
                  <l>make haſte, farewel, adieu, adieu.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a Stanza of thirteen to the dozen: might not this think you be ſung to the tune of <q>
                  <l>Down Turn-bull ſtreet as ſhe did paſſe,</l>
                  <l>ſhe heard a Bird ſing in a Glende,</l>
                  <l>the chiefeſt of whoſe Note it was,</l>
                  <l>no pleaſure to a bounteous friend, in a corner.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But ſet jeſting apart, here you do plainly ſee by <hi>Mrs. Jones</hi> her own acknowledgement, what Propriety <hi>Mr. Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi> had in her: again, here ſhe vaunts her practiſes upon his old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge by lighting his ſnuff with her Adulterous intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And laſtly, ſee how in a ſecret conſciouſneſs of her wickedneſs ſhe directs him to burn her Letters, that her wicked deeds might not come to light.</p>
            <p>I conclude w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> a Letter from Mrs. <hi>Pigeon,</hi> the great architect of all this villany, written with her own hand for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Goodwin,</hi> with order to tranſcribe it &amp; ſend it to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>War<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>up</hi> the Bayliff of the Burrough; for not only <hi>Mr. Goodwins</hi> tongue, but his hands muſt be crampt, and he muſt not dare to write one word but by their Copies, though as wiſe as <hi>Solomon,</hi> they dare not truſt him with the leaſt ſervice, which by the way confirms me in the opinion, That when the Project was brought to examination before the Commiſſioners, they ſaw an abſolute neceſſity of his being tranſlated to another world. The Letter begins thus: <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>MVch honored Sir, being Coheirs with me of my gray-hairs, it is my great encouragement to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118634:20"/> you to end this ſtrife, and at leaſt to Repay my two third parts of the Goods taken in Execution by the Son of my own Loyns, taken by me into Copartnerſhip in a Third of my Trade, and the Stock given by my ſelf: Know Sir, it was to have Reſt in my old age by him who is the ſaddeſt Trouble: Now God hath made you my Vmpier, for the Lords ſake let it be ſuch as may not bring my gray Hairs with Sorrow and Suits to the Grave; but with Peace give me back my two Thirds, for which I ſhall ſay, Let a Bleſſing reſt on the head of yours for the ſake of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your Servant, <hi>Weſſel Goodwin.</hi>
                           </hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Thus though this Serpent wind in ſecret pathes, upon the Rock in many places her ſlime diſcovers her: You have heard before, how <hi>Andrew Goodwin</hi> being in that manner caſt out, confeſs'd a Judgement to a Creditor, and the Goods thereupon taken in Execution, and by <hi>Mrs. Pigeons</hi> Craft undervalued and ſold by the Bayliff to <hi>Hen. Coleborn</hi> for 403. l. of which the Creditor Recovered only the one Third part; and <hi>Mrs. Pigeon</hi> by this Letter procures the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two parts to be paid back to her; and accordingly ſhe Received it, pretending for <hi>Mr. Goodwin.</hi> But what ſhould fools do with money: let <hi>Mr. Coleborn</hi> and <hi>Mrs. Pigeon</hi> have money that are wiſe and ſubtile, and know how to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it.</p>
            <p>Many other Letters to this purpoſe there are from <hi>Mrs. Pigeon</hi> and <hi>Mrs. Jones,</hi> but fearing to nauſeate the Reader with this gear, I forbear. I ſhall conclude with <hi>Mrs. Pigeon,</hi> and as it is a cuſtome in forrein parts when notorious male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors have by ſome ſtratagem eſcaped the hand of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, then they draw their picture as near as may be to the life, which being fixed upon publick places of Execution, gives notice to all men what manner of perſon he was, that ſo he may be diſcovered: So will I, as near as I can, draw <hi>Mrs. Pigeons</hi> picture, which I refer to all to judge: for her outward Perſon, ſhe is ſomewhat taller than the ordinary ſize of women, a little thick ſhouldered, and inclining to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118634:20"/> fatneſſe; indeed her out-ſide is tolerable, were it beautified with an honeſter mind. In this and the former Relation you may judge ſomewhat of her Nature by her practiſes, but all that falls ſhort, nor is it poſſible to deſcribe all the furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of that dark Charnel-houſe of ſin: 'tis true that ſhe hath very good natural endowments, an excellent memory to retain, a quick fancy to invent, an eloquent tongue to perſwade, which improved in honeſt actions would much adorn her; but being abuſed, to deceive, to work miſchief, ſpoyl, ruine, and as is feared murder alſo, renders her but ſo much more guilty to God, and hateful to all good men: theſe abilities joyned with her artificial helps, as an inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting geſture, harmonious accent in ſpeech, tears, ſmiles, deep ſighs, ſhutting her eys as if ſhe were the contracted mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of piety and modeſty: theſe will ſhe uſe with ſuch cunning advantage, that ſhe creeps into the boſoms of many that hear her, and with theſe ſhe hath been heard to ſay ſhe can make a fool of the wiſeſt man alive: and when ſhe hath bleared and muffled the underſtandings of thoſe that heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to her; ſhe turns her about to her Goſſips, and brags how ſhe hath caught them. She hath the skill to obſerve all tempers, and frames her ſpeech, geſture, actions ſutably, ſhe will endeavour to catch a wiſe man with ſophiſticated Reaſon, as <hi>Mr. Hen. Coleborn;</hi> a weak man with a preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded love and care of their good, as <hi>Mr. Goodwin;</hi> a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man with bribes, as <hi>Mr. H;</hi> a cholerick man with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, as <hi>Mr. Pigeon;</hi> yet notably commanding her own temper, ſo that as I have ſeen her, eſpecially when ſhe hath ſome Web of miſchief upon the Loom, let the injured perſon vilifie her never ſo much with upbraiding of her wickedneſs, call her never ſo many uncouth Names, ſhe diſcovers no more paſſion then if ſhe underſtood not one word of what is ſpoken.</p>
            <p>A Religious man ſhe orders as ſhe pleaſes, let him be of what Principle he will, ſhe will turn her ſelf into ſuch an Angel of light, that he ſhall cry out ſhe is a moſt Angelical Creature; would ſhe work a Revenge (as ſhe is of a moſt vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictive nature) ſhe conſiders what defamations are moſt eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118634:21"/> received, and hardeſt to wipe off; amongſt others, her moſt frequent is, Such a man took Phyſick, his wife knew not of it, it muſt needs be the French Pox; and to perſons of whom was never the leaſt cauſe of ſuch ſuſpition, ſhe will ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore company, Have you never had the French Pox? ſpeak as in the ſight of God: let them Reply what they will, ſome dirt will ſtick; ſhe is the very <hi>Proteus</hi> of this age, can ſhape her ſelf into all forms; in one Company ſpeak of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but heaven; in another, as at <hi>Iſlington</hi> before good company, call for a filthy bawdy ſong; nay, ſhe can make every thing about her act a part; would ſhe win compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from her Judge, ſhe appears all in mourning, melting like <hi>Niobe</hi> in tears; nay, where it may ſtand her inſtead, by art can make her face as black as her garments, as tis affirmed ſhe did before the Court Martial; but if ſhe be before ſuch as ſhe thinks another bait may take better, ſhe will appear in gorgeous Apparel, her neck and breſts bare, her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion beyond a natural fairneſſe; theſe are ſome of her Moral parts: I conclude with her Religion, which to tell you what it is, were to ſhape a Coat for the Moon; and as one ſaith, 'Tis impoſſible to draw a face that is ſo often va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. I have thought ſometimes that had ſhe been of the Maſculine Sex, ſhe is rightly qualified for a dangerous He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick. She is Proud, Wilful, Eloquent, and vafrous; with theſe ſhe hath run through all the forms of theſe times; and having examined their Principles how they would tend and ſquare with her Projects, hath quitted one after another, and is now ſetled in Quakeriſm, which ſhe extols for the only way that fits her deſigns; in this fond way there is a Principle that carries it ſmooth, a declining of the written Word of God for an infallible rule of Practiſe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (as was proved before the Commiſſioners) ſhe ſaid ſhe cared not if the Bible were burnt: and being guided by a light within, Ah, quoth <hi>Mrs. Pigeon,</hi> here's a way fits me; I have a light within that directs me to Renounce my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, make another mans eſtate my own, to rob, ſpoyle, ruine, work miſchief, murder, any thing, the light within guides me to it, and warrants me in it: As for that other
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118634:21"/> Principle of the ſimpler ſort of Quakers, of making Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is to be imputed to their ignorance, being but Babes in knowledge to me; and their weakneſs is to be pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied. Theſe are ſome few life-touches, by which you may know <hi>Mrs. Pigeon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Conclude with a Three-fold humble Requeſt; 1. To every godly Magiſtrate in this Nation, that ſhall come to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of theſe things, that they will (out of zeal to the glory of God, the honour of Religion, the publick well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, love to Juſtice, hatred to Sin, compaſſion to the poor ruined perſons herein mentioned, as they ſhall have oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity) do impartial juſtice upon theſe women, that they may be a terrour to all evil doers, and a ſhelter to the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. 2. To every godly Miniſter in this Nation by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to watch diligently over the ſouls of their people, that they keep up with all care the authority of the Scripture as the infallible Rule of all our practiſe, and that they in their places beg of God either to convert or bring to ſpeedy ſhame ſuch Apoſtates that have brought ſo much ſhame and diſgrace upon Religion.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly, To every Religious Lawyer, that ſhall by reading this, come to the knowledge of this woful Caſe, that they will in tender commiſeration of the ſufferings and wrongs of theſe poor undone Children (who by the wicked inſinuations of theſe women were made Fatherleſs many years before their Father died, and are divers of them now reduced to extreme poverty) finde a vacant our to conſider of ſome way of Relief in ſome Court of Juſtice or other, and that they will give them their beſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and this let them be aſſured of, though they have no Money, they ſhall have a double fee of hearty Prayers for rich bleſſings from him that hath promiſed to hear the Fatherleſs and oppreſſed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:118634:22"/>
            <head>A Poſt-ſcript to Mr. <hi>John Hat.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu were lately warned by a wiſe religious Gentleman to take heed by <hi>Mr. Coleborns</hi> example of burning your fingers in <hi>Mrs. Pigeons</hi> Projects, you ſlighted that Admonition; you are now warned again, remember <hi>Mr. Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born,</hi> no perſwaſion of Friends could prevail with him to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon <hi>Mrs. Pigeons</hi> company; fat Fees would not let him ſee his folly till death and a guilty Conſcience ſtared him in the face, and then too late he abhorred them: <hi>Mr. Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win;</hi> Children, in the bitterneſs of their ſorrows, did make their complaint to God, and they did then ſummon <hi>Mr. Coleborn,</hi> theſe women, and your ſelf, (they being by cunning tricks of Law made diſtitute of Relief on earth) to appear at the impartial Bar of Gods Tribunal to anſwer this great wickedneſſe; ſince that <hi>Mr. Coleborn</hi> is gone, and you and they muſt ſuddenly follow: what think you, will this buſineſs of <hi>Mr. Goodwins</hi> and his Childrens Ruine hold Water when you ſhall come to gaſpe for breath, as <hi>Mr. Coleborn</hi> before you? and that you ſhall remember there was a poor weak man, Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> he had four dutiful Children, and by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt forty years painful labour and the aſſiſtance of a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous provident Wife in an honeſt calling he had gathered a competency of 2000. l. to ſupport his Family: Miſtris <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon,</hi> a woman of an infamous name, without conſent of her Husband fees me, by ſubtil ſlights of Law ſhe compaſſes this Eſtate, I go up &amp; down with her from place to place and juſtifie her Purchaſe, avowing that ſhe hath as good a Title to <hi>Mr. Goodwins</hi> Eſtate as any of the Commiſſioners had to theirs; and tell them, the Complaints of <hi>Goodwins</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are but as the ſhearing of Hogs, A great cry, and a little wool; I counſelled her, after ſhe had gotten all the Stock, to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118634:22"/> pick the bones, fall upon the houſe, break up Coppars, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns, Pipes, convey, ſell, make havock of all, not leave ſo much as the little houſhold Goods given by old <hi>Mrs. Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi> at her death (by her Husbands conſent) to his Children, but carry all away; and when any made ſcruple to buy theſe ſtoln Goods I tendred them my Security to warrant their Bargain: let the Children beg, ſtarve, no matter, I have my Fee: I perſwaded <hi>Mr. Pigeon</hi> with all the Art I could to have no hand in aſſiſting thoſe beggarly people old <hi>Goodwins</hi> Children, and when that would not prevail, threatned him with the Jayle, and effected it. I ſay, when you ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member all this, and a great deal more I am not privie to, what will you ſay? you ſay now ſhe is your Clyent, and yet Lawyers do not uſually lodge their Clyents in their houſes, and ſend their Children to board at their houſes, nor wait upon them about ſtreets from place to place. I could ſay ten times more, if you have any ſpark of Grace or Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, repent and endeavour a reſtitution, and know that your doom is before you, and by that time you can well turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you, there will be no Remedy.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="spa" type="letter">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118634:23"/>
            <head>Sennor Juan Gold.</head>
            <p>HArto ſe maravillan muchos perſonas Diſcretos que un hombre de vueſtra calidad quiere poner ſu nombre y reputacion en tanta peligro para con ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nazes rabioſas y loores mentiroſas ſoſtentar la fama deſtas malditas mugeres, como ſy le yua de la vida en deſpecho de la verdad aueri guarlas por ſantas y angellicas aunque ſu hechas las declaran por Diabolicas: Sy <hi>V. M.</hi> fueſſe hombre necio como el pobre S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Goodwin</hi> difunto la eſcuſa ſeria facill, pero ſiendo hombre d'entendimiento da lugar a muchos de creer que no es ſin cauſa q'uel marido le ha defendido la frequentacion de ſu muger, paraque <hi>V. M.</hi> ſe deſanganne enteramente mira y conſidera la Hiſtoria precedente, y ſy de aqui adelante no aboreſce y huye eſtas infamas mugeres yo con otros creere, que no es oro todo que reluze.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118634:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
